Guide to the Henry Noble MacCracken Papers, 1907 - circa 1968
Archives and Special Collections Library, Vassar College Libraries
- SERIES XII. BIOGRAPHICAL INFORMATION AND PERSONAL PUBLICATIONS, 1907-1946
  - Speeches, 1923-1935
    - Education, the Foundation of Democracy - Kentucky Education Association, 20 Apr 1927 (Folder 116.35)
    - The Tale of a River - Exchange Club, Louisville, 21 Apr 1927 (Folder 116.36)
    - A Vassar Luck Penny - Founder's Day, 29 Apr 1927 (Folder 116.37)
    - "One Equal Temper." Commencement Address, June 1927 (Folder 116.38)
    - The Art of Being Understood - Albany Academy, 14 June 1927 (Folder 116.39)
    - A New Map of Vassar, Convocation, Sep 1927 (Folder 116.40)
    - Sermon, 16 Oct 1927 (Folder 116.41)
    - Rights of Parents - Lecture Course of Nursery School, 16 Jan 1928 (Folder 116.42)
    - A College for Liberals - Educ. Conference, Brooklyn, N.Y., 18 Jan 1928 (Folder 116.43)
    - A.A.V.C. New York City, 4 Feb 1928 (Folder 116.44)
    - Is Vassar Progressive? - Lincoln School, NYC, 14 Feb 1928 (Folder 116.45)
    - Philosophy and Food - Phi Beta Kappa Dinner, 7 March 1928 (Folder 116.46)
    - Founder's Day, 27 Apr 1928 (Folder 116.47)
    - Paderewski Dinner, 16 May 1928 (Folder 116.48)
    - Law in Vassar College, Commencement, 1928 (Folder 116.49)
    - Alice in Wonderland - An Allegory in Education, Roland Park Country School, Baltimore, 13 June 1928 (Folder 116.50)
    - Winter of Our Discontent (Folder 116.51)
    - A Balanced Life - Convocation, 24 Sept 1928 (Folder 116.52)
    - Students Bill of Rights (Folder 116.53)
    - "Bystanders and Understanders" - Radio Broadcast - "Collier's Hour," WJZ, 17 Feb 1929 (Folder 116.54)
    - Thrift and Education (Folder 116.55)
    - "Public Schools and Higher Education" (Folder 116.56)
    - Assoc. Alumnae, NYC, 5 Nov 1921 (Folder 116.57)
    - Selection and Civilization (Folder 116.58)
    - Latin Poems of Thomas Gray (Folder 116.59)
    - The American Conception of Higher Education (Folder 116.60)
    - Whatsoever Thing is Good - Sermon, VC Chapel (Folder 116.61)
    - De RE Sophistica - Commencement, 11 June 1929 (Folder 116.62)
    - Are College Women Exclusive? - Radio, 7 Nov 1929 (Folder 116.63)
    - "Budgets," Assembly, 7 Apr 1930 (Folder 116.64)
    - Founder's Day Speech (Folder 116.65)
    - The American Conception of the University - I.S.S. at Mt. Holyoke, 2 Sep 1931 (Folder 116.66)
    - "Seeing Things at Vassar," Alumnae Council, Oct 1929 (Folder 116.67)
    - Speech before Schoolmasters Council, 8 Oct 1915 (Folder 116.68)
    - "The Forest of Arden," Convocation, 7 Oct 1931 (Folder 116.69)
    - “Will the American College Survive?” 1st Presbyterian. Church, Buffalo, 10 Jan 1932 (Folder 116.70)
    - "College Material" (Folder 116.71)
    - The Strategy of the Unexpected Washington (Folder 116.72)
    - "Will the American College Survive?" Phi Beta Kappa Dinner at A.Y.U. Centennial, 2 March 1932 (Folder 116.73)
    - "The American Fraternity System," Psi Upsilon Dinner, NYC, 9 Apr 1932 (Folder 116.74)
    - Debate at St. Stephen's w/ Dr. Nocke (?), 17 Apr 1932 (Folder 116.75)
    - Frontiers and Free Thought, NSFA Broadcast, WMCA, 21 Nov 1932 (Folder 116.76)
    - Address at Chamber of Commerce, Cleveland, 12 Dec 1932 (Folder 116.77)
    - Discovery of the Individual (Folder 116.78)
    - "Youth in the New Era," National Red Cross, Washington, 25 Apr 1933 (Folder 116.79)
    - Guernsey Milk (Folder 116.80)
    - Physical Education as a Fine Art (Folder 116.81)
    - Assembly Talks (Folder 116.82)
    - Chapel Talks (Folder 116.83)
    - Misc. Speeches (Folder 116.84)
    - Misc. Speeches (Folder 116.85)
    - Commencement- Old Men for Action, Young Men for Counsel, 1934 (Folder 116.86)
    - Misc. - "Lincoln's Birthday," "Three Values," etc. (Folder 116.87)
    - "The Crisis in Education" (Folder 116.88)
    - Miscellany Speeches (Folder 116.89)
    - "Advice from a Caterpillar," Radio WOR, 21 June 1934 (Folder 116.90)
    - Mexican Lecture at University of Mexico, July 1934 (Folder 116.91)
    - A Mexican Vignette - Summer Institute of Euthenics, July 1934 (Folder 116.92)
    - Tower of Learning (Folder 116.93)
    - The Parent (Folder 116.94)
    - The Students' Share in College Gov't, NSFA, 28 Dec 1934 (Folder 116.95)
    - The Child Labor Amendment, Radio Broadcast, 28 Jan 1935 (Folder 116.96)
    - Miscellany Speeches, 10 March 1935; Chicago Ithaca, 27 Feb 1935 (Folder 116.97)
    - "The Language of Personality," Univ. of Chicago Convocation, 10 March 1935 (Folder 116.98)
    - Miscellaneous Speeches (Folder 116.99)
    - Commencement, 10 June 1935 (Folder 116.100)
    - Miscellaneous Speeches (Folder 116.101)
    - Convocation Speech, 23 Sep 1935 (Folder 116.102)
    - The Book of Life Sermon (Folder 116.103)
    - Radio Dialogue (Folder 116.104)
    - Misc. Speech (Folder 116.105)
    - Miscellaneous Speeches (Folder 116.106)
    - "Ulster Traditions in the U.S." (Folder 116.107)
    - Miscellaneous Speeches (Folder 116.108)
    - Miscellaneous Speeches (Folder 116.109)
    - Chapel Talks, 1933/1934 (Folder 116.110)
    - "Thinking is Real," Convocation, 24 Sep 1934 (Folder 116.111)
    - Miscellaneous Speeches (Folder 116.112)
    - Miscellaneous Speeches (Folder 117.1)
    - Sarah Lawrence College, Speech at 10th Anniversary Dinner, 9 Dec 1936 (Folder 117.2)
    - Miscellaneous Speeches (Folder 117.3)
    - Training for Civic Responsibility, St. Louis A.A.V.C., 14 Nov 1936 (Folder 117.4)
    - Miscellaneous Speeches (Folder 117.5)
    - Mediaeval Casements - Town Hall Lectures (Folder 117.6)
    - Miscellaneous Speeches (Folder 117.7)
    - Miscellaneous Speeches (Folder 117.8)
    - Miscellaneous Speeches (Folder 117.9)
    - Convocation, Sep 1937 (Folder 117.10)
    - Miscellaneous Speeches (Folder 117.11)
    - American Student Union, Welcome to Conference, 28 Dec 1937 (Folder 117.12)
    - Miscellaneous Speeches (Folder 117.13)
    - Miscellaneous Speeches (Folder 117.14)
    - Miscellaneous Speeches (Folder 117.15)
    - Miscellaneous Speeches (Folder 117.16)
    - Miscellaneous Speeches (Folder 117.17)
    - Miscellaneous Speeches (Folder 117.18)
    - Miscellaneous Speeches (Folder 117.19)
    - Miscellaneous Speeches (Folder 117.20)
    - Miscellaneous Speeches (Folder 117.21)
    - Miscellaneous Speeches (Folder 117.22)
    - Miscellaneous Speeches (Folder 117.23)
    - Miscellaneous Speeches (Folder 117.24)
    - Of Human Intercourse (Folder 117.25)
    - Conference on Canadian-American Affairs (Folder 117.26)
    - Miscellaneous Speeches (Folder 117.27)
    - Recreation and Better Human Relations (Folder 117.28)
    - The Faith of an Independent, Plymouth Church of the Pilgrims (Folder 117.29)
    - Miscellaneous Speeches (Folder 117.30)
    - The Religious Front, Brooklyn Church and Mission Federation, 30 Jan 1941 (Folder 117.31)
    - Miscellaneous Speeches (Folder 117.32)
    - Miscellaneous Speeches (Folder 117.33)
    - Miscellaneous Speeches (Folder 117.34)
    - Miscellaneous Speeches (Folder 117.35)
    - Miscellaneous Speeches (Folder 117.36)
    - "Racism and the Origin of the Aryan Myth" (Folder 117.37)
    - Miscellaneous Speeches (Folder 117.38)
    - Miscellaneous Speeches (Folder 117.39)
    - "The Law in Liberty," Commencement, 1943 (Folder 117.40)
    - Baccalaureate Sermon at Vassar College, 1946 (Folder 117.41)
    - Miscellaneous Speeches (Folder 117.42)
    - Miscellaneous Speeches (Folder 117.43)
    - Miscellaneous Speeches (Folder 117.44)
    - Miscellaneous Speeches (Folder 117.45)
    - Miscellaneous Speeches (Folder 117.46)
- SERIES XIII. UNPROCESSED PERSONAL MATERIAL, circa 1920 - circa 1968
  - Correspondence, clippings, material relating to publications, etc. (Box 118)
  - Alphabetical correspondence (1960s), writings, etc (Box 119)
  - U.S. Committee for the Care of European Children, speeches, Vassar alumnae correspondence, etc (Box 120)
  - Correspondence, clippings, etc (Box 121)
  - Plans, maps and other material relating to "Hornyback" and possibly other properties (Box 122)
  - Alphabetical correspondence (1960s) and material re: the Kosciuszko Foundation (Box 123)
  - Old Dutchess Forever correspondence (Box 124)
  - Writings, notes, correspondence (Box 125)
  - Awards, clippings, programs, congratulatory correspondence (Box 126)
  - Manuscript material from Rebel at Law and Prologue to Independence (NY: James H. Heineman, 1964) (Box 127)
  - Research files on Dutchess County and NY history (Box 128)
  - HNM speeches on reel-to-reel tape, transferred from the Music Library 5/7/1991 (see also boxes 144-145) (Box 129)
  - Notes for book (Old Dutchess Forever) and miscellaneous notes on NY history (Boxes 130-133)
  - Correspondence from HNM (Box 134)
  - Photographs (Boxes 135-137)
  - Correspondence from HNM (Box 138)
  - Correspondence from HNM to Maisry MacCracken (Boxes 139-140)
  - Scrapbooks, Experimental Theatre photos, miscellaneous, school notebooks, unidentified manuscript, etc. (Box 141)
  - Miscellaneous research files and notes (Boes 142-143)
  - HNM speeches on reel-to-reel tape, transferred from the Music Library 5/7/1991 (see also box 129 ) (Boxes 144-145)
  - Class notebooks, unidentified manuscript, material re: the Kosciuszko Foundation, etc. (Box 146)
  - Engagement books (Box 147)
  - Autograph album/scrapbook (Box 148)
  - Card index to articles and speeches (Box 149)
  - Honorary plaques, (2) (Box 150)
  - Printers blocks (Box 151)
  - Photographs, medals, pins and ribbons (Box 152)
  - Miscellaneous manuscripts (Box 153)
  - Correspondence, 1960s (Box 154)
  - Clippings (Box 154)
  - Clippings, correspondence, 1920s-1930s (Box 155)
  - Manuscripts, correspondence, notes, etc (Box 156)
  - Mackinac College material, 1960s (Box 157)
  - United States Committee for the Care of European Children material, 1940s (Box 158)
  - Scrapbook "Religious Liberty in the U.S." (Box 159)
  - Scrapbook, 30th anniversary of the Kosciuszko Foundation (Box 160)
  - Miscellaneous index cards (Box 161)
  - Photographs and newsclippings (Box 162)
  - MacCracken Family Christmas cards, miscellaneous correspondence (Box 163)
  - Scrapbook/photo album presented to HNM "from the Vassar Experimental Theatre, 1915-1946" with a foreword written and signed by Hallie Flanagan Davis (Box 164)
  - Oversized family photographs and certificates (Box 165)
  - Oversized family photographs and "t.p. mechanicals" (Box 166)
  - Condolence letters (A2004-005), "Nor Long Remember" manuscript, HDN correspondence, scrapbooks, Hornyback index cards, etc. (Box 167)
  - Oversized photographs (Box 168)
  - Oversized photographs (Box 169)
  - Diplomas and Foreign Scholarship Fund Proclamation (Map Case - Drawer 36)